please do for and cite should not display man'''7
Regression Estimators
At thirty man suspects himself a fool;
Knows it at forty, and reforms his plan:
At fifty chides his infamous delay,
Pushes his prudent purpose to resolve,
In all the magnanmity of thought
Resolves, and re-resolves: then dies the same.
J. Young
7.1 INTRODUCTION
Like ratio estimators, linear regression estimators also make use of auxiliary information for increasing precision. It was seen that the ratio estimator provides a precise estimate of the population mean if regression is linear and the line passes through the origin. When regression is linear and the line does not go through the origin, it is better to use estimators based on linear regression. In other words, if the study variate () is approximately a constant and a multiple of the auxiliary variate, it is more precise to estimate the population mean or total by fitting a linear regression. Such an estimator is called a regression estimator. We shall now discuss the main characteristics of such estimators and compare them with the mean per unit estimator and ratio estimator.
7.2 DIFFERENCE ESTIMATOR
Let  and  be correlated characteristics. We wish to estimate . If, from a simple random sample, we obtain the unbiased estimators  and  of  and , respectively, then we can improve upon the estimator  by introducing a difference function. Thus, a simple difference estimator is defined by

(7.2.1)
It is assumed that there is a unit change in  when a unit change is made in ,  and  having equal variances. This assumption will not be valid if the relationship is of the type , where  and  are constants. In this situation, a more generalized difference estimator is defined as

where  and  are known quantities. (7.2.2)
In simple random sampling, the difference estimator and its variance are discussed in the following theorems.
THEOREM 7.2.1 In simple random sampling, wor, the difference estimator  is unbiased and its sampling variance is given by


(7.2.3)
where  is the correlation coefficient between  and , and 
The proof is simple, and its development is left as an exercise.
From this result, it may be noted that  has smaller variance than  if 
COROLLARY Show that  will have its minimum value when

This proves that the optimum value to be given to  is , the value of the regression coefficient of  on . In this case,  and the minimum value of variance is .
THEOREM 7.2.2 In simple random sampling, wor, the sampling variance of  is obtained by

(7.2.5)
where  is some specified quantity.
Proof Since  is a given constant and , therefore, the unbiasedness of  is proved. Further, denoting


and

we have

Hence,



This proves the theorem.
COROLLARY 1 For the case , the variance of the difference estimator  is exactly the same as the first order approximation of  given in relation (6.4.4).
COROLLARY 2 The difference estimator  will be more precise than the mean per unit estimator  if .
This gives the condition that the difference estimator will be more efficient than the mean per unit estimator if , otherwise, the mean per unit estimator will be efficient. Hence, it may be concluded that the difference estimator will be simple to apply as its results are exact. If one can guess  from a pilot survey, then a proper decision about its use can be taken.
An illustration of some characteristic situations in the application of difference estimates has been given by Zarkovic (1956).
COROLLARY 3 In simple random sampling, wor, an unbiased estimator of  is obtained by


(7.2.6)
where

and

7.3 REGRESSION ESTIMATOR
While discussing the difference estimator, it was seen that the optimum value to be given to  is , where  is the regression coefficient of  on . Generally,  is not known in advance and its value is estimated from the sample. Suppose  and  are obtained for each unit in the sample, then a least square estimate of  is

Thus, linear regression estimators of the population mean  and population total  are given by

and

(7.3.1)
Here,

Therefore, we shall present the theory of the linear regression estimator , only. Since  is a random variate, exact expressions for the bias and variance of the regression estimator are difficult to derive. In this section, large sample approximations to its bias and sampling variance will be given.
7.3.1 Bias of Regression Estimator
The regression estimator is consistent because, by increasing the sample size  to the population size , we have . Ultimately, the regression estimator reduces to .
The regression estimator  is biased since

(i)  is generally estimated by taking the ratio of the estimate of  to that of  and
(ii) it involves the product of two estimates, viz. . The bias of the regression estimator will usually be trivial and will decrease as sample size increases.
THEOREM 7.3.1 In simple random sampling, the bias of  is approximated by
which will be negligible if the sample size is large.
Proof Suppose

where

Substituting these values in Eq. (7.3.1), we get

(7.3.3)
Therefore, the bias of the regression estimator is

(7.3.4)

since

For large samples, usually  decreases. It becomes zero if the joint distribution of  and  is a bivariate normal.
COROLLARY 1 If , the regression estimator  reduces to the ratio estimator  and its bias is given as in Eq. (7.3.2).
COROLLARY 2 If the sample is selected in the form of  independent sub-samples, then the bias can be unbiasedly estimated by

(7.3.5)
This estimator of bias can be used to get the unbiased regression estimator. A similar method has been discussed by Mickey (1959) and Williams (1961). The technique developed by Murthy (1962) can also be applied to make unbiased regression estimators.

7.3.2 Sampling Variance of Regression Estimator
When the sample size is large enough, the contribution of the term involving  in relation (7.3.3) is expected to be very small and the bias in the regression estimator  reduces to zero. Therefore, if the terms of the second and higher orders are neglected, we can derive the sampling variance of the regression estimator.
THEOREM 7.3.2 In simple random sampling, the large sample variance of the regression estimator is given by

(7.3.6)
Proof If the term involving  in relation (7.3.3) is ignored, we have

Therefore,



COROLLARY 1 In simple random sampling, wor, the sampling variance of the regression estimator  is given by


(7.3.7)
This shows that if regression is linear and  is the least square estimate of  then the regression estimator  is more precise than the difference estimator . If the regression of  on  is perfectly linear, i.e. , the variance of the regression estimator becomes zero. Also if  and  are uncorrelated, the variance of  reduces to that of the mean per unit estimator .
COROLLARY 2 In large samples, an almost unbiased estimator of  is given by



(7.3.8)
The last form in the above relation is good for computational purposes. According to standard regression theory, it is suggested that the divisor  be used instead of .
Williams (1963) has suggested a method for getting some precise unbiased regression estimators. A detailed discussion of these estimators is given by Rao (1969).
7.4 COMPARISON WITH THE MEAN PER UNIT AND RATIO ESTIMATORS
For a large sample size, the variance for estimators of the population mean  can be written as



Firstly, comparing with the mean per unit estimator, we observe that the variance of the regression estimator is always smaller unless . In case , the variances for both are equal. The reduction in variance is large when  is high, and small when  is low.
Comparing next with the ratio estimator, it can be seen that the variance of the regression estimator is less than that of the ratio estimator if

or

(7.4.1)
which is always true unless . In this situation, both estimates have the same variance and this occurs only when the regression of  on  is a straight line through the origin.
This comparison suggests that all these estimators belong to the class of estimators

(7.4.2)
where  is a random variate having some values in a finite range.
By a suitable choice of , one can generate different types of estimators. If the variate  is zero,  conforms to the mean per unit estimator, . If  is a constant,  becomes a difference estimator. When  is , the estimator  becomes the ratio estimator . Similarly, when  is equal to the sample regression coefficient , it becomes the linear regression estimator . In large samples, the regression estimator is the most efficient and can be used if computational labour is not heavy.
The above comparisons suggest that the regression estimator is not always a proper choice although it provides a variance equal to or less than that of others. Some rules for a choice among alternatives are as follows:
When advance information on an appropriate value of  is available, then, with simple computations good results can be obtained with such values of  with the difference estimator.
When the correlation coefficient between variates is nearly equal to the ratio of their standard deviations, i.e. , the difference estimator with  will attain equally precise results as the regression estimator.
When the correlation coefficient between variates is nearly equal to the ratio of their coefficients of variation, i.e.  the ratio estimator will provide equally precise results as the regression estimator.
When  is different from , the regression estimator should be preferred. In this situation, the difference estimator with  will not provide precise results.
When  is different from  the regression estimator should be preferred. In this situation, the variance of the ratio estimator will be larger than that of the regression estimator.
When computations for the regression estimator are heavy, time consuming and expensive, its use is recommended only if the gains from such computations are much more significant than the additional costs.

EXAMPLE 7.1 Using the data given in Example 6.1, estimate the total number of milch animals in 117 villages of zone A by the method of regression estimation. Also, compare its precision with the ratio estimate and mean per unit estimate.
Here,




Hence,


Regression estimate of the total number of milch animals is obtained as



and an estimate of the variance of  is given as


From Example 6.1,

and

Hence, the relative precision of the regression estimate over the mean per unit estimate is

Similarly, the relative precision of the regression estimate over the ratio estimate is given by

7.5 REGRESSION ESTIMATORS IN STRATIFIED SAMPLING
When the population is stratified into  strata and, in the th stratum,  units are selected from  units with simple random sampling, wor, like the ratio estimators, two regression estimators are possible. One is the separate regression estimator which is obtained by estimating the regression coefficients for each stratum separately. Another is the combined regression estimator which is obtained by getting a common (pooled) regression coefficient for all the strata.
7.5.1 Separate Regression Estimator
A separate regression estimator  ( for separate) in stratified sampling may be defined as

(7.5.1)
where , , ,  and  are the corresponding terms for the th stratum. Like the usual regression estimator,  is biased. If  is chosen in advance, and not based on the sample values,  is an unbiased estimator of .
THEOREM 7.5.1 If sampling is independent in different strata and sample size is large enough in each stratum, then  is an almost unbiased estimator. To the first order of approximation, its variance is given by

(7.5.2)
The proof is obvious.
COROLLARY 1 If , the true regression coefficient in the th stratum is satisfied and the variance may be written as

(7.5.3)
COROLLARY 2 Provided the sample size  is large in all strata, an estimator of variance is given by

(7.5.4)
The estimator  also suffers from the same drawback as the corresponding ratio estimator, the ratio of the bias to its standard error becoming quite large. Since the leading terms in bias come from the quadratic regression of  on , this may be of the same sign in all strata. Hence, the overall bias in the estimator  may be very large.

7.5.2 Combined Regression Estimator
A combined regression estimator  ( for combined) in stratified sampling may be defined as

(7.5.5)
where  and  are the stratified sample means of  and  variates, and  is the pooled estimate obtained by

The important point is to obtain the value of . An easier method is to select a few extreme values of , some high and some low. A straight line through the average values is drawn. The slope of this line is taken as the estimate of , which is given by

,
where  and  are two points on the line.
It can be shown that the combined regression estimator  is also a biased estimator of . It is analogous to . All the results can be drawn on similar lines.
THEOREM 7.7.2 If sampling is independent in different strata and sample size is large enough in each stratum, the variance of  is given by

(7.5.6)
The proof is obvious.
COROLLARY 1 If  and weight , a combined regression coefficient,  minimizes the variance of .
COROLLARY 2 Provided sample size  is large in all strata, the estimator of variance is given by

(7.5.7)
The estimator  also suffers from the same defect as the corresponding ratio estimator. This estimator will not be appropriate when there is reason to believe that the regression coefficient  varies considerably from stratum to stratum.
7.5.3 Comparison of Combined and Separate Estimators
Some caution is required when deciding whether the separate or combined regression estimator is to be used at any specific situation. The bias in the separate regression estimator is likely to be larger when sample size in each stratum is small. On the other hand, the defect of the combined estimator is that its variance is inflated if the population regression coefficients differ from stratum to stratum. If the regressions are approximately linear and the regression coefficients appear to be the same in all strata, use of the combined regression estimator is preferred. If the regressions are linear but the coefficients differ from stratum to stratum, it is advisable to adopt the separate estimator. Though the separate regression estimator is likely to be more efficient than the combined regression estimator, the latter is likely to have smaller bias.
EXAMPLE 7.2 With the data given in Example 6.2, estimate the total number of trees in the districts by the regression method of estimation and compare its precision.
We can use the calculations and results obtained in the above mentioned example. Also,

(i) Separate Regression Estimate The estimate of the total number of trees is given by

and



Therefore, efficiency over ratio estimate is given by

(ii) Combined Regression Estimate An estimate of the total number of trees is given by

and


Therefore, efficiency over ratio estimate

Similarly, the efficiency of the separate regression estimate  over the combined regression estimate  is

7.6 MULTI-VARIATE REGRESSION ESTIMATOR
Frequently, data on more than one auxiliary variate are available and it is considered important to make use of all available information. If  is the usual estimator of the mean of the main variate,  is an unbiased estimator of the mean  of the auxiliary variate  and  is the regression coefficient of  on , .
An estimator of the form defined by

(7.6.1)
is used as a multi-variate estimator.
Des Raj (1965) proposed another difference estimator of the form

(7.6.2)
where  are given regression coefficients and  are the weights adding up to unity.
For simplicity, we shall consider the case of two -variates. In this case, the estimator may be written as

(7.6.3)
with its variance given by


where , , ... are given in relation (6.11.4). (7.6.4)
Putting  in the variance expression above, differentiating with respect to  and equating the result to zero, we have the best weights given by

and

(7.6.5)
By substituting the values of these weights in the variance expression, we have the minimum variance

(7.6.6)
Let us assume that  and the correlation coefficient between  and  is . If  and the coefficient of variation of  is , the optimum values of weights are given by

By substituting these values in the variance, we have

(7.6.7)
Further, if only one  variate is used, the variance is given by

(7.6.8)
Comparing relations (7.6.7) and (7.6.8), we find it always better to use the second variate if . Similarly, when no  variate is used and a comparison is made with the case of one  variate, it is better to use one  variate if .
SET OF PROBLEMS
7.1 Show that, if the proportional increase in the variance of the regression estimator  arising due to the use of  instead of  is to be less than , then the relative deviation is

(Cochran, 1963)
7.2 A random sample, wor, is selected from a finite population of  units, which itself is assumed to be a sample from a super population by following the model

where  and  are positive constants.
Show that the regression estimator of the population mean  is always more precise than the ratio estimator when  is used as an auxiliary variate.
(Des Raj, 1958)
7.3 Using the difference estimator  and the regression estimator , an estimator is defined as .
Show that

and


Hence, or otherwise, prove that

(Des Raj, 1968)
7.4 An eye estimate of the fruit weights () on each tree in an orchard having 100 trees was made. The total weight () was found to be 12,500 kg. A random sample of 10 trees was taken and the actual weights of fruits () along with the eye estimates were as below:
Actual weight ()
Eye est weight ()
51 42 46 39 71 61 58 57 58 67
56 47 48 40 78 59 52 58 55 67
(i) Estimate the total actual fruit weight  by taking the estimator

and find its sampling variance.
(ii) Estimate the total actual fruit weight  by taking the linear regression estimator

Also find the sampling variance and compare the results.
7.5 In Exercise 6.12, estimate the total number of guava trees by regression estimate and calculate the standard error. Compare the efficiency of the regression estimate with the ratio and mean per unit estimates.
7.6 Will the linear regression estimator with least square estimate  give a more precise estimate in Exercise 6.13?
7.7 Using two auxiliary variates  and , the multi-variate estimator given in Eq. (7.6.3) is used for estimating the population mean . If the coefficients of variation of  and  are equal to , the correlation coefficients between  and , , equal to , and  are taken as , .
Show that the optimum weights are given by . Derive the variance of the estimator in this case and show that the estimator would be more efficient than the mean per unit estimator  if , where  is the correlation coefficient between  and  and  is the coefficient of variation of .
(Des Raj, 1965)
7.8 For estimating the total cattle population, a random sample, wor, of 24 villages was selected from the total 1238 villages. The number of cattle obtained in the survey is given below for each sample village, together with the corresponding census figure relating to a previous period:
S. N. of villagesCensusNumber of cattle surveyS. N. of villagesCensusNumber of cattle surveyS. N. of villagesCensusNumber of cattle survey16236549161210173753302690696102985551821221835305341120452110191471604315293121069592202972105697813706707214012626842640141795189022252204769247515140611232319918583712921611811524564574
Compare the efficiency of the regression estimator with the ratio estimator. It is given that the number of cattle for the previous period of 1238 villages is 680,900.
7.9 In Exercise 6.14, estimate the area by the method of regression estimation and compare its efficiency with the ratio estimate obtained therein.
REFERENCES
Cochran, W.G., Sampling Techniques, John Wiley and Sons, New York, (1963).
Des Raj, "On the relative accuracy of some sampling techniques," J. Amer. Statist. Assoc., 53, 98-101, (1958).
"On a method of using multi-auxiliary in sample surveys," J. Amer. Statist. Assoc., 60, 270-277, (1965).
Sampling Theory. Tata McGraw-Hill Publishing Co., New Delhi, (1968).
Mickey, M.R., "Some finite population unbiased ratio and regression estimators" J. Amer. Statist. Assoc., 54, 594-612, (1959).
Murthy, M.N., "Almost unbiased estimators based on interpenetrating sub-samples," Sankhya, 24, 303-314, (1962).
Rao, J.N.K., "Ratio and regression estimators," New Development in Survey Sampling, John Wiley and Sons, New York, (1969).
Williams, W.H. "Generating unbiased ratio and regression estimators," Biometrics, 17, 267-274, (1961).
"The precision of some unbiased regression estimators," Biometrics, 19, 352-361 (1963).
Zarkovic, S.S., "An illustration of some characteristic situations in the application of the difference estimates," Rev. Inter. Statist. Inst., 24, 52-63, (1956).
